<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The godly and Christian decease of the illustrious and high-borne Prince, Mauritius of Nassau, Prince of Orange, of happy memory. For the comfort and edification of all true Christians. / First written in Dutch, by master Iohn Bogerman, minister of the word of God, at Leeuwarden: and now translated into English..</title>
            <title>Het christelijk overlijden van den prince Mauritius van Nassau. English</title>
            <author>Bogerman, Johannes, 1576-1637.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1625</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B07402</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC"> 166384371</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3204.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S91125</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">166384371</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocn 166384371</idno>
            <idno type="VID">191504</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B07402)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 191504)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2268:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The godly and Christian decease of the illustrious and high-borne Prince, Mauritius of Nassau, Prince of Orange, of happy memory. For the comfort and edification of all true Christians. / First written in Dutch, by master Iohn Bogerman, minister of the word of God, at Leeuwarden: and now translated into English..</title>
                  <title>Het christelijk overlijden van den prince Mauritius van Nassau. English</title>
                  <author>Bogerman, Johannes, 1576-1637.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[31] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.S. for Nathanael Newbery, and are to be sold at his shop at his shop at the signe of the Starre, in Popes head Pallace, and vnder Saint Peters Church in Cornehill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London: :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1625..</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title vignette with roayl arms on t.p. and colophon, headpieces, printed marginalia.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴ D³.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Trinity College (Dublin, Ireland). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Maurice, --  Prince of Orange, 1567-1625 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  Wars of Independence, 1556-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:191504:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:191504:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE GODLY AND CHRISTIAN DECEASE of the Illuſtrious and High-borne PRINCE, MAVRITIVS of NASSAV, Prince of ORANGE, of happy Memory.</p>
            <p>For the comfort and edification of all true CHRISTIANS.</p>
            <p>Firſt written in Dutch, by Maſter IOHN BOGERMAN, Miniſter of the word of God, at <hi>Leeuwarden:</hi> And <hi>Now Tranſlated into Engliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>T. S.</hi> for <hi>Nathanael Newbery,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the ſigne of the Starre, in Popes head Pallace, and vnder Saint <hi>Peters</hi> Church in Cornehill, 1625.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="approbation">
            <pb facs="tcp:191504:2"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ee here vnder-written, profeſſors of Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity in the Vniuerſity of <hi>Leyden,</hi> hauing read and examined this Relation of the Chriſtian deceaſe of the Illuſtrious and High-born Prince <hi>Maurice</hi> of <hi>Naſſau,</hi> Prince of <hi>Orange;</hi> written by the worſhipfull Doctor, <hi>Iohn Bogerman,</hi> being the very words which his Princely <hi>Excell:</hi> being deadly ſicke, ſpoke; doe declare by theſe preſents, that we doe hold this Relation to be very neceſſary to bee publiſhed in Print; not doubting but it will be very ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable vnto all impartiall Readers, and will bee read with great edification of all perſons, both high and low, and will not onely ſerue them for a patterne, but alſo as a motiue to ſtirre them vp vnto hearty Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and true faith in Ieſus Chriſt, to the glory of God, and the ſaluation of their owne ſoules.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Datum</hi> 
                  <date>26. <hi>Maij</hi> 1625.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>IOH. POLIANDER.</item>
                     <item>ANT. WALaeVS.</item>
                     <item>ANDREAS RIVERTVS.</item>
                     <item>ANTONIVS THYSIVS.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:191504:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the High and Mighty Lords</hi> THE ESTATES GENERAL of the vnited Prouinces. AND <hi>To the High-borne Prince,</hi> FREDERICK HENRY, Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi> And alſo <hi>To the Illuſtrious Lord,</hi> ERNEST CASIMIR, Count of <hi>Naſſau, Catzenelnbogen,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Oſt High and mighty, and moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Lords, I doe preſent vnto your Excell: and by you vnto all faithfull Inhabitants of theſe vnited Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the deſcription of the Chriſtian deceaſe of the Illuſtrious and High-borne Prince, <hi>Maurice</hi> of <hi>Naſſau,</hi> Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> &amp;c. Both, whoſe life and death, ſhall be of immortall memory. This is a ſmall matter in regard of my ſelfe and my labour, but very great in reſpect of that great Prince, who doth here ſpeake his laſt words, in a matter of
<pb facs="tcp:191504:3"/> greateſt moment, and who doth here fight the greateſt fight that can befall, and ſo doth finiſh the greateſt worke that can be done on earth, and after his labour is ended, wee ſee him goe from miſery into ioy and reſt, leauing the whole world in a tumult of vnreſt. It hath beene alwaies held a commendable cuſtome to make knowne the laſt words and actions of great perſonages, that it might ſerue for an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample vnto others: therefore all impartiall people ſhall vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that it is more then reaſon, to publiſh and make knowne vnto the world, the laſt words and deeds of the High-renowned Lord, the Prince of <hi>Orange;</hi> eſpecially ſince it is both of high and low ſo much deſired and longed for, that all true-hearted people (who haue receiued the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of <hi>impartiality,</hi> may iudge, whether among all the words of his Excell: any be to be found, that are not very religiouſly ſpoken, and ought of euery of vs to be followed. We may well ſay, the Lord hath loued this Prince vniill the end. In his life he hath made him a patterne of all heroicke and Militarie actions, and Politicke wiſedome: in his death hee hath in an extraordinary manner made him an obiect of his mercy, and an example of Chriſtian Piety and Godlineſſe. In his life time he gaue him the victorie ouer his bodily and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward enemies, and at his death he made him extraordinarily victorious, triumphing ouer his ſpirituall enemies. So gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding him by his holy ſpirit, that with an extraordinary reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute courage, hee did deſpiſe all earthly things, ſaying many times:
<q>
                  <hi>I will not be troubled with any worldly matters.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>So that leauing the world, and the heauy burthen of his weighty affairs together, he did wholly apply himſelfe to fight this ſpirituall fight: as wiſely and couragiouſly as euer hee did in temporall combats. For in all his ſpirituall actions he
<pb facs="tcp:191504:3"/> did moſt looke at that, whereat we moſt ſtumble, when wee haue to doe with the Lord, <hi>Our Sinnes,</hi> which being put quite from vs, wee obtaine free acceſſe vnto the Lord, yea, we become familiar with him, as the child with the father. <hi>Bleſſed is he that getteth the practiſe of this;</hi> In this worke his P. <hi>Excell:</hi> hath followed the ſteps of the <hi>moſt Valianteſt Champions</hi> which haue beene among the people of God. As, <hi>Dauid, Daniel, Eſay, Ieremy,</hi> and others, Whereof we haue ſpeciall examples in the <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> where we ſee that Gods children hauing to doe with God, doe ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten looke vpon their ſinnes, and ſo humble themſelues there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, that thereby afterwards they come to receiue in their hearts a filiall faith, feare, and obedience. His P. <hi>Excell:</hi> did know that our ſpirituall enemy, which wee beare about vs, was ouercome, and that death had loſt her ſting, and hell her victory. This enemy, <hi>Sinne,</hi> we doe ouercome: Firſt, by true repentance, and doe hate him as our deadlyeſt enemie; Secondly, when we by true faith, caſt them vpon the ſhoulders of that vnſpotted <hi>Lambe Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> who can only beare them, &amp; carry them away; &amp; thirdly, when on the contrary we become louers of righteouſnes, and whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer is acceptable vnto the Lord. Theſe three perticulars may euery one finde that is any thing experienced in holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that the Holy Ghoſt hath in aſpeciall manner wrought in this Prince. His <hi>Excell:</hi> knowing that there is but one way to heauen for the greateſt potentate, and the meaneſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, hath not flattered himſelfe, nor ſought to iuſtifie his ſinnes, but hath, as one of the leaſt of Gods ſeruants, with an humble hart and vnfained repentance, confeſſed them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord, and hath, in true faith taken his refuge onely to Ieſus Chriſt, in whom his ſoule found reſt. And thereunto hee ſo often declared his hearty deſire, to ſerue the Lord bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:191504:4"/> then he confeſſed to haue done, as the Lords great bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits vnto him did require.</p>
            <p>And this is the ſpeciall mercy of God, which all good chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans may boaſt of, that the Lord (who knew the good deſire of his <hi>Excell:</hi>) hauing freed him from all worldly hinderances, for a crowne vnto all his laudable deeds, hath ſuffered his <hi>Excell:</hi> to vſe ſuch a ſolemne and holy action as this is, not onely for the reſt and ſaluation of his owne ſoule, but alſo for the edification of all good chriſtians. And therefore I doe not without cauſe ſay once more that the Lord hath loued this Prince vnto the end. For I do from my hart confeſſe that in all the times I viſited his <hi>Excell:</hi> His <hi>Excell:</hi> did ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haue himſelfe, that I did not once goe from him, without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing edified, not doubting but it will doe the like to all good chriſtians that ſhall happen to reade it. Wherefore I doe comfort my ſelfe, and doe praiſe the Lord, that within this my weakeneſſe of body, wherewith I did not thinke to haue done any more publike ſeruice, he hath ſo strengthned mee, to doe this ſpirituall ſeruice vnto this famous Prince, and through him vnto all good people in generall, who I truſt in their ſorrow, which without doubt they haue for the loſſe of this Valiant Champion, will finde themſelues comforted, when they ſhall heare from his <hi>Excell:</hi> mouth ſo many Chriſtian ſpeeches, and ſhall ſee him dye the death of the Righteous. Whereby I hope, (that we may ſo ſay) hee ſhall haue left and pronounced a bleſſing ouer the church of God, and this ſtate. As alſo in perticular vnto his <hi>Excell:</hi> Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious ſucceſſor, which we with true repentance (according to the example of his <hi>Excell:</hi>) will expect from the merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full God, beſeeehing him in the meane time, for Chriſt Ieſus ſake, mercifully to pardon our crying ſinnes, and plentifully to powre into our hearts the grace of repentance, and not
<pb facs="tcp:191504:4"/> yet leaue his Heritage, nor to let the Rod of his affliction to lye too long vpon our backes.</p>
            <p>This may comfort all good Chriſtians in their affliction, who at this preſent liue in griefe and perſecution, that this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Prince did beare ſuch affection vnto them, ſaying, <hi>when he</hi> heard any good newes from abroad:
<q>
                  <hi>That will be good for gods children.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Which his <hi>Excell:</hi> declared likewiſe to beare vnto the church of God, and to the preſeruation of the true religion, (which he hath ſufficiently ſhewen vnto the whole world by many actions) agreing with that which the Lord Embaſſador of his Maieſty of Great Brittaine, Sir <hi>Dudley Carleton</hi> was pleaſed in his ſpeach to relate vnto your H. Dignities from the very mouth of his P. <hi>Excell:</hi> which his <hi>Excell:</hi> alſo was pleaſed to communicate vnto mee, which words were theſe.
<q>Theſe be two great Maximies, the preſeruation of the reformed Religion, and the warres againſt Spaine.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Vpon which two heads his <hi>Excell:</hi> did meane that the wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of the countries depended, I haue in this relation ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly ſet downe the very words of his <hi>Excell:</hi> as hee ſpake them, which when I came home I ſet downe vpon a peece of paper, and haue conferred them with thoſe that were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent when his <hi>Excell:</hi> ſpake them.</p>
            <p>That which I ſpake, I haue ſet downe as I thought beſt for edification, at the firſt viſitation I did not intend to haue troubled his <hi>Excell:</hi> ſo much, as hauing experience of the diſability of a ſicke perſon, but his <hi>Excell:</hi> detained mee, partly with extraodinary attention hee had to here the word of God, and partly with his queſtions which hee propounded. The other viſitations were not ſo long in regard his <hi>Excell:</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:191504:5"/> grew euery day more weaker and weaker, and therefore when hee could not ſpeake any longer, wee betooke our ſelues vnto prayers, expecting a bleſſed end.</p>
            <p>I thought good to direct this worke vnto your High and Mighty Dignities, with whom his <hi>Excell:</hi> during the time of his gouerment hath conuerſed, who are witneſſes of his lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable actions, and partakers of his immortall praiſes: and who his <hi>Excell:</hi> hath inſtituted Executors of his Princely will and teſtament, ſoe that of right it doth belong vnto your honours: and without doubt, not onely this, but alſo the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars of the religious deceaſe of this moſt excellent Prince will be pleaſing vnto your honours, with whom your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes haue euer liued in ſuch a neere correſpondencie, and haue yet by your honnors Committies, (namely by the Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Lords, <hi>Henric</hi> of <hi>Eſſen,</hi> from <hi>Gelderland, Nicholas van-Bouckhorſt, Lord</hi> of <hi>Nortwich,</hi> from <hi>Holland, Rienck van-Burmania,</hi> from <hi>Freeſland, Aſſueer van-Harſolte,</hi> from <hi>Ouer-Iſſe</hi>) viſited and remained with his Excell: vntill his end. Concerning your P. <hi>Excell:</hi> Gracious Lord, who hath a ſpeciall intereſt in this labour, as being the onely brother vnto the deceaſed Prince, whom hee hath loued with a brotherly loue, (as is manifeſt) and beſides, heire of his Princely dignity, and his ſucceſſor in that great and waightie calling, being a little before his Excell: death, to the comfort and ioy of his Excell: and vnto all true chriſtians, vnited in matrimony with the Illuſtrious Princeſſe <hi>Amelia,</hi> Princeſſe of <hi>Orange,</hi> Counteſſe of <hi>Solms,</hi> who, with her <hi>Excell:</hi> the Princeſſe of <hi>Portugall</hi> were both together with his <hi>Excell:</hi> the day before he dyed, and were witneſſes of his Princely and chriſtian carriage. Wherein her Excell: did take ſuch pleaſure, that ſhe did ioyfully glory therein vnto the other Lords, ſaying, <hi>That it was a bleſſed thing for euery
<pb facs="tcp:191504:5"/> Chriſtian, to diſpoſe himſelfe ſo well at the time of his death.</hi> The like did her <hi>Excell:</hi> the Princeſſe of <hi>Portugall</hi> your <hi>Excell:</hi> ſiſter, <hi>That ſuch a chriſtian carriage came from God, and was his gift,</hi> which the Lord <hi>Agathius,</hi> Lord of <hi>Dhona,</hi> rehearſed vnto me from the mouth of her <hi>Excell:</hi> Your <hi>Excell:</hi> ſhall not onely finde in this relation the chriſtian and religious deceaſe of this worthy Prince, but alſo that which may ſerue your P. <hi>Excell:</hi> and other Lords, for an example of imitation, and comfort, in the matter of ſaluation, being of more value then all the tranſitory goods of this world.</p>
            <p>Therefore I doe humbly beſeech your high and mighty P. <hi>Excell:</hi> graciouſly to accept of this my meane labour, and I will pray vnto the Almighty God, to preſerue your <hi>High</hi> and <hi>Mighty P. Excell:</hi> in vnion together, to gouerne you with his Holy Spirit, and ſo to bleſſe and proſper you, in this time of trouble of the whole chriſtian world, that you may happily and couragiouſly preſerue the free liberty of the Goſpell in theſe countries, and ſo to ſupply the places of the deceaſed Prince, and Count <hi>William,</hi> &amp;c. who are now both at reſt with the Lord, and herewith I turne my ſelfe to the relation of that which happened before and at the death of his <hi>Excell:</hi> Remaining euer more</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your high and mighty</hi> P. Excell: <hi>moſt obedient ſeruant in the Lord,</hi> Ioannes Bogermanus.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>At the Hage,</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>the 16. of</hi> May, <hi>1625.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:191504:6"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:191504:6"/>
            <head>A TRVE RELATION OF The Godly and Chriſtian deceaſe of the Illuſtrious and High-borne <hi>Prince,</hi> MAVRITIVS of NASSAV, late Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> of happy Memory.</head>
            <div n="1" type="visitation">
               <head>
                  <hi>A Relation</hi> Of that which happened at the firſt viſitation of the Illuſtrious Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> on Munday the 14. of Aprill, Anno 1625. in the afternoone, about foure of the clocke.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas diuers perſons of quality, did often times requeſt mee, to viſit the <hi>Illuſtrious Prince of Orange,</hi> in the time of his ſickneſſe, which I feared to doe, in regard of my weakeneſſe; yet, not to incommodate my ſelfe, and ſpecially his <hi>Excell:</hi> I thought (the more, becauſe I very well knew his <hi>Excell:</hi> did yet ſometimes reade Letters, and becauſe I had vnderſtood by the <hi>Worſhipfull Doctor Walleus,</hi> profeſſor
<pb facs="tcp:191504:7"/> of Diuinity in the Vniuerſity at <hi>Leyden,</hi> that his <hi>Worſhip</hi> comming from thence, at the requeſt of ſome of the Lords of the Councell, had viſited his Princely <hi>Excell:</hi> whom after many religious and godly ſpeeches he had left very well pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared) with a briefe and ſhort Letter of exhortation and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, in ſtead of a parley in preſence, to haue taken my leaue of his <hi>Excell:</hi> But as I was buſie herewith, Maſter Secretary <hi>Iunius</hi> ſent for me to come vnto his <hi>Excell:</hi> who was very de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to haue me come vnto him. Conſidering that it was Gods will, and knowing it to be my bounden duty, in regard his <hi>Excell:</hi> hath obliged vs ſo much vnto him, I omitted that which I had in hand, and preſently I went with the ſame meſſenger that came for me: Beſeeching the Lord to ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then me, and to grant his bleſſing, that it might bee for his honour and glory, for the comfort of his <hi>Excell:</hi> and for the edification of all good men.</p>
               <p>Being come to the Court, and hauing ſomewhat reſted my ſelfe, I was by the aforeſaid Lord <hi>Secretary,</hi> and the <hi>Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlaine</hi> brought into the Chamber where his <hi>Excell:</hi> lay, who very kindely entertained mee, putting forth his hand and bid me welcome, and made me to ſit downe at his Beds ſide. Whereupon the people diſmiſſed the Chamber, except the aforeſaid <hi>Secretary,</hi> Doctor <hi>Rumpf,</hi> and the <hi>Chamberlaine,</hi> who remained at the Beds-ſide, to heare and take notice of, all the ſpeeches that happened, although vnſeene of his <hi>Excell:</hi> his <hi>P. Excell:</hi> demanded of me, how I did, what ſickeneſſe I was troubled withall, and whether I amended, as alſo of my appetite, meate, drinke, and ſleepe: Of which when I had ſatisfied him, his <hi>Excell:</hi> begunne to ſpeake of his owne ſickeneſſe; demanding of me what Doctor <hi>Rumpf</hi> thought of it: Which when I had told him, his <hi>Excell:</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, <hi>I am of that opinion alſo.</hi> Complaining of his Ague and hot Feuer, which did much trouble him; and it ſeemed, his <hi>Excell:</hi> bewayled them that were conſtrayned to vſe much Phyſicke. Whereupon I ſaid; we muſt looke vnto God, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out whoſe pleaſure there cannot one hayre fall from our heads, and in regard of his diuine decree, our time cannot
<pb facs="tcp:191504:7"/> be ſhortened. Whereupon his <hi>Excell:</hi> anſwered, <hi>I hold it to be ſo alſo, and I am reſolued:</hi> Hereby I tooke occaſion,<note place="margin">His Excell: faith of Gods prouidence.</note> to ſhew vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his <hi>Excell:</hi> the miſery which man is ſubiect vnto in this life, and how happy we are, that we haue that ſure comfort which the Lord hath ſo abundantly reuealed vnto vs in his Goſpell. Whereupon his <hi>Excell:</hi> ſaid, <hi>It is true.</hi> Then I ſaid fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, You may pleaſe to conſider, the great mercy God ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vnto your <hi>Excell:</hi> all the time of your gouernement, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king you an incomparable <hi>Prince</hi> of your time, whoſe acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons the whole world admires, and ſpecially in regard the Lord hath freed you from ſo many eminent perils and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and doth now ſo mercifully ſhew this great fauour and mercy vnto you, in viſiting you with ſo Fatherly a chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; leading you, as it were with his hand vnto a bleſſed end, giuing you ſo long and moderate a ſickeneſſe, wherein hee doth continue your vnderſtanding and perfect ſpeech, not onely to ſerue the Countrey, as your <hi>Excell:</hi> yet doth, but alſo to practiſe that which is for your euerlaſting ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: where to the contrary, that good Lord, of happy memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, <hi>Count William Lodwicke</hi> of <hi>Naſſau,</hi> at the beginning of his ſickeneſſe did looſe his ſpeech, his ſtrength, and his vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding: whoſe laſt words were vpon the comfort which I ſpake vnto him,<note place="margin">Count <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ams</hi> laſt words in his ſicknes</note> 
                  <hi>LORD be mercifull vnto me for thy beloued Sonnes ſake;</hi> which we miſerable wretches doe not in due time conſider. Now I doe not doubt but your <hi>Excell:</hi> doth make a good vſe of this affliction, that you may enioy the perfect fruits of the Chriſtian Religion which your <hi>Excell:</hi> hath ſo long maintained and propagated; and this fruit is a comfort both in life and death vnto our conſciences, conſiſting here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, that we wretched ſinners, may haue a reconciled and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull God. If the fauourable countenance of a King be the life of the Subiects (as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith) how much the more (ſaid I) is the mercifull fauour of God? Then I ſaid further, (conſidering his <hi>Excellencie</hi> did hearken ſo attentiuely vnto me) <hi>Gracious Lord,</hi> the reformed Religion doth moſt cleare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and profoundly ſet forth vnto vs, our miſery, and doth giue vs the onely and ſoueraigne remedy againſt the ſame,
<pb facs="tcp:191504:8"/> with the onely way for our reconciliation with God, through <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> his onely beloued Sonne our Sauiour, who doth beſtow all his benefits on them that lay hold vpon him in true faith and repentance, of whom God doth teſtifie in the holy Scriptures:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.17.</note> 
                  <hi>This is my beloued Sonne, in whom I am well pleaſed;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 14.6.</note> 
                  <hi>He is the way, the truth, and the life; No man commeth to the Father, but through him, neither is there ſaluation in any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 4.11.</note> 
                  <hi>for there is no other name giuen vnder heauen where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by wee muſt be ſaued;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30.</note> 
                  <hi>Who of God is made vnto vs Wiſedome and righteouſneſſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.11.</note> 
                  <hi>Sanctification and Redemption; For, other foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on can no man lay, then that which is laid, which is</hi> IESVS CHRIST;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 13.39. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3 24. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.7. <hi>Col</hi> 1.14. <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.11.</note> 
                  <hi>By him euery one that beleeueth is iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied; By whom wee haue Redemption and reconciliation with God through his bloud, euen the forgiueneſſe of ſinnes:</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of <hi>Iohn</hi> witneſſeth, <hi>Hee that hath the Sonne, hath life.</hi> And therefore we can haue no other communion with God, then through him; and this is the onely, ancient, true, and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Goſpell, which God himſelfe hath reuealed vnto our fore-Fathers in Paradiſe, and afterwards by his Patriarkes and Prophets hath publiſhed vnto his people, by all the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies in the old Teſtament, and hath ſithence in the new Teſtament ſo gloriouſly reuealed it vnto vs Gentiles, which in fore times were not of the people of God, and doe now through his infinite mercy ſo abundantly enioy it.</p>
               <p>Hereupon I rehearſed vnto his <hi>Excell.</hi> that the Memorable late <hi>Count William Lodowicke</hi> of <hi>Naſſau,</hi> in his ſicknes receiued tydings that the Arch-duke <hi>Albertus,</hi> being very ſicke, went vnto the ſhrine of our <hi>Lady,</hi> at a place ſo called, whereto ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny goe in pilgrimage; <hi>Scherpenheuvel,</hi> there to receiue accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Popiſh cuſtome, remiſſion of his ſins, wherat the Noble <hi>Count</hi> hartily laughed, reioycing and praiſing God (although in faint words) that he had laid a better foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in his heart, and had receiued a better light. Whereupon his <hi>Excell:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Notable words of his <hi>Excell:</hi>
                  </note> ſaid, <hi>Count William</hi> had <hi>Scherpenheuvel</hi> continually with him; His <hi>Excell:</hi> thinking that I did not vnderſtand him, rehearſed them again more plainer. <hi>I ſay</hi> (ſaid he) beating two or three times vpon his breſt, <hi>Count Willia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> had <hi>Scherpenheuvel</hi> continually with him: Iuſt ſaid I, Noble Lord, <hi>Count William</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:191504:8"/> had no neede to goe to <hi>Scherpenheuvel</hi> for comfort, for hee had his onely comfort <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> in his heart: <hi>ſoe doe I meane too,</hi> ſaid his <hi>Excell.</hi> After theſe ſpeeches I ſhewed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his <hi>Excell:</hi> the example of <hi>Hezekiah,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Kings</hi> 20. <hi>Eſay</hi> 38.</note> whom God by his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet cauſed to be told, <hi>That hee ſhould put his houſe in order, for he ſhould dye &amp; not liue.</hi> The King was deadly ſick, but yet did not dye, for that was hidden in Gods diuine decree, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon when the king had humbled himſelfe before the Lord, the Lord added fifteene yeares more vnto his life. So (ſaid I) if the Lord ſhould tell your <hi>Excell:</hi> ſo, in this ſickneſſe, which is a meſſenger of God, and a fore-runner of death, and death will follow, but the Lord in his mercy hath hidden from vs the time when.</p>
               <p>Whereupon when his <hi>Excellence</hi> had giuen mee to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that hee felt hee ſhould dye of this ſickneſſe,<note place="margin">His <hi>Excel:</hi> is of opinion that hee ſhould dye of this ſicknes, and doth deſire to be prepared for it.</note> I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted him to reconcile himſelfe with God, with whom at this preſent hee had to doe, that hee might then with a qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et Conſcience, expect whatſoeuer the Lord ſhould diſpoſe of his perſon. Whereupon his <hi>P. Excell:</hi> anſwered, <hi>So I doe,</hi> then I ſaid further, it is requiſite that aboue all things we doe humble our ſelues before the Lord by reaſon of our ſinnes which are contrary vnto the moſt holy commandements of God. And in their nature are abhominable in the ſight of the Lord, who are the occaſion of Gods wrath, and of all plagues temporall &amp; Eternall, for which the ſonne of God ſuffered ſo much on the Croſſe. Wee muſt haue an vpright hatred of them, condemne them and be aſhamed of them, &amp; according to the example of the Saints confeſſe them before the Lord. And the ſtrickter wee are in this perticular, and the more wee powre out our hearts before the Lord, the more capable wee ſhall be with ioy and thankefulneſſe to receiue the riches of Gods mercy.</p>
               <p>And when I had ſhewed vnto his <hi>Excell:</hi> ſome parts of Scripture wherein is promiſed mercy and forgiueneſſe of ſinnes vnto them that ſhall truly repent, his <hi>Excell:</hi> opened his mouth and ſaid, <hi>I haue Sinned,</hi> and preſently after with a more vehemency, that the very teares ſtood in his eyes,
<pb facs="tcp:191504:9"/> hee ſaid, <hi>I haue Sinned groſſely:</hi> Whereby I was much moued, declaring vnto him that this was an acceptable offering vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.</note> 
                  <hi>Such a broken heart will the Lord not deſpiſe:</hi> Shewing him the abundant ioy and comfort all repentant ſinners haue in the Lord <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> who is the onely and perfect attonement for our ſinnes: Hee is our <hi>Righteouſneſſe,</hi> who can onely ſtand before the Lord, and he is our life, which I had a little before more largely inſiſted vpon: but hauing ſhewed a few more, as, <hi>Eſay,</hi> 53.1. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.1. 2 <hi>Hebrewes</hi> 10. I demanded of his <hi>Excell:</hi> if in his heart, hee did not comfort himſelfe with them. Whereupon his <hi>Excell:</hi> with his hands cloſed, confeſſed his faith, ſaying, <hi>I take my refuge vnto the great mercy of God:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">His <hi>Ex:</hi> doth confeſſe his faith and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in Chriſt Ieſus. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.6.</note> 
                  <hi>And I beleeue that Ieſus Chriſt died for mee on the croſſe, in whom I put all my truſt:</hi> and theſe words hee ſaid twice together. Whereupon I ſaid, this is a true chriſtian faith, the Lord, from whom all good gifts commeth be praiſed, that hee hath giuen vnto your <hi>Excell:</hi> ſo great a gift as this faith is, and grant to ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill this worke in you. Then I ſaid further, in ſuch a heart as this is, doth the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> worke all deſire and loue vnto <hi>righteouſneſſe:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">His <hi>Ex:</hi> earneſt deſire to ſerue the Lord bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then he confeſſed to haue done. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 130.</note> Whereupon his <hi>P. Excell:</hi> ſaid. <hi>It repenteth mee that I haue not ſerued the Lord better then I haue done: I confeſſe I haue not ſerued him enough: I will pray him to ſtrengthen mee.</hi> This (ſaid I) is moſt Chriſtianly ſpoken, and ſo muſt all faithfull Chriſtians doe: <hi>If thou O Lord</hi> (ſaith Dauid) <hi>marke mine iniquities, O Lord who ſhall ſtand?</hi> But, <hi>mercy is with thee that thou mayſt bee feared.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If there were no mercy with God, no man were able to ſerue him, but now the forgiueneſſe of ſinnes is an Article of our chriſtian Faith, we are all miſerable ſinners before the Lord, and doe all ſtand in need of his mercy: <hi>It is true</hi> ſaid his <hi>Excellencie.</hi> Then I ſpoke vnto his <hi>Excell:</hi> comforts from the word of God, that his <hi>Excell:</hi> might patiently take this croſſe vpon him, not doubting but that it would bee for the comfort and ſaluation of his ſoule, ſaying, that his <hi>Excell:</hi> would doe well to delight himſelfe in the meditating vpon that great worke of God which hee did for vs, in ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering
<pb facs="tcp:191504:9"/> his Sonne not to be an Angell, for Angels, but to be man, for to redeeme many, whoſe manhood, doctrine, miracles, obedience, bloodſhedding death, reſurrection, and aſſention to heauen is all for our good, onely in faith con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly beleeuing them as if they had here happened before our eyes, and as if wee with the Apoſtles had ſeene the word of life with our corporall eyes,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.13.</note> whereof <hi>Iohn</hi> ſpeaketh 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.1.3. The ſelfe ſame IESVS doth now ſit at the right hand of God, deſiring and expecting that all thoſe that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in him, to be with him, and to behold his glory, of which glory in regard of our ſoules after death, as alſo in regard both of ſoule and body at the day of iudgment,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 17.24.</note> I rehearſed vnto his <hi>Excell:</hi> certaine places of Scripture: Whereupon when his <hi>Excell:</hi> had ſpoken theſe words,<note place="margin">His <hi>Ex:</hi> words of the ioyes of heauen.</note> 
                  <hi>We can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not conceiue this, it is aboue apprehenſion,</hi> I ſaid, the Angels themſelues cannot conceiue this great wonderfull worke of God, but doe delight in the contemplation thereof: We muſt beleeue and admire it, giuing thankes vnto the Lord that he hath revealed ſo much vnto vs as doth (againſt the miſery which wee haue in this life) in ſome meaſure giue vs a taſte of the ioyes of the life to come: and thereupon I rehearſed vnto his <hi>Excell:</hi> what ioy and gladneſſe the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles had vpon the Mount, when they did but onely ſee a glympſe of the heauenly glory; and ſo I alluded alſo that many times in my ſickneſſe I was there-with ſo reioyced and comforted, that I felt a taſte of the heauenly ioyes within mee.</p>
               <p>Whereupon his <hi>Excell:</hi> enquired for ſome places of Scripture which I had mentioned vnto him, eſpecially of thoſe that ſpoke of the Prayer of Chriſt, and of the ioyes of the life to come, which I repeated vnto him, telling him, that hee ſhould not diſturbe himſelfe too much, and if hee could not endure much ſpeech, to imploy his minde with good thoughts, or if he could to let ſome body reade by him that which ſhould fall into his <hi>Excell:</hi> minde, for the word of God is fruitfull: and ſo here with I thought to haue taken my leaue, excuſing my ſelfe, fearing leaſt I ſhould haue beene
<pb facs="tcp:191504:10"/> ouer-trouble-ſome vnto his <hi>Excell:</hi> but his <hi>Excell:</hi> detai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned mee longer with theſe queſtions, <hi>There bee ſome, ſaid he, that haue much in their mouthes, but they haue no deeds, their words and their deeds doe not agree, and ſuch there be many.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whereunto I anſwered that thoſe kinde of people were of two ſorts, ſome are but hipocrites which doe not meane with their hearts what they ſay, but doe onely ſeeke to pleaſe men: thoſe bee but like painted tombes, of whom Chriſt ſpeaketh. The Goſpell is like vnto a net which catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth both good and bad fiſhes. In the Lords field groweth both wheate and tares, and therefore we muſt not bee offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded at it, for ſuch there hath beene in the Apoſtles times, and euer will bee. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erywwell</hi> (ſaid his Excell:) <hi>thoſe haue it not in their hearts, but when they repent they ſhall be ſaued.</hi> Theſe people are dead in their ſinnes (ſaid I) they haue no ſpirituall life, and are not yet borne againe, and if they will be ſaued they muſt bee made aliue by the ſpirit of God, and be borne againe. But it is otherwiſe with them that haue a good reſolution in their hearts and thereupon vowe to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme it, although the deed doe faile them, they may ſtumble and fall, but the one more then the other, yea they may fall heauily, whereof wee haue examples in the word of God theſe haue the ſpirit of God and are borne anew, but they are feeble and weake, like vnto a weakely man, he hath a good will to goe, but hee cannot ſo fully performe it, and they are grieued for theſe imperfections and are ſorry for them. The Apoſtle himſelfe, ſheweth vs the inward combats be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the fleſh and the Spirit; <hi>for, what I would, that doe I not, but what I hate that doe I.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The ſpirit of God is not alwaies a like, for as the winde doth ſometimes blow harder then other, ſo it is with the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, and God doth deale thus with his children, to humble them and make them know that it is not in their ſtrength, but that it is a ſpeciall gift of his grace. The ſeed that falleth into the ground doth bring forth a ſeuerall quantity of fruit, in ſome a hundred, in ſome ſixty, and in ſome but thirty. Chriſt will not breake a bruiſed reed, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:191504:10"/> will he quench ſmoaking flaxe, and therefore the Lord doth not deſpiſe ſuch. We are all weake, and are to ſtriue with fleſh and bloud all the dayes of our life, but this fight doth not happen alwayes alike, ſometimes when wee truſt too much to our owne power, and doe neglect the meanes which the Lord hath ordained to preſerue vs, the Lord doth giue the Diuell leaue to tempt vs, and this the Lord doth doe, that we (being lifted vp againe) might confeſſe our weakeneſſe, and be the more carefull of our wayes, as wee may ſee by the examples of <hi>Dauid</hi> and <hi>Peter,</hi> and in the meane time they that turne vnto the Lord and beleeue in him, haue eternall life.</p>
               <p>Hereupon his <hi>P. Excell:</hi> ſaid, <hi>So doe I vnderſtand it alſo,</hi> but, <hi>there be ſome that thinke they can haue faith and repentance when they pleaſe, they thinke it is in their power, but I know it muſt all come from God, and it is he that muſt giue it.</hi> It is true, ſaid I, your <hi>Excell:</hi> ſaith very well, and hee vnto whom the Lord doth giue it, doth feele it, and doth ſhew it according to the meaſure as he hath receiued it: but they that let themſelues be perſwaded they can haue it at their pleaſure, are deceiued; for who is he that hath a ſparke of Gods grace in his heart, that would not be willing to be releaſed from his ſins, and to doe good continually, if hee could doe it at his pleaſure? The daily experience teacheth all good Chriſtians that doe throughly examine their liues, that many times they cannot doe as they would doe. I haue a little before ſhewed vnto your <hi>Excell:</hi> the example of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> vpon this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, who complaineth, that he cannot doe what hee would doe. It is the Lord that worketh in vs both the will and the deed; for wee haue not one good thought of our ſelues, Chriſt ſaith. <hi>Without mee you can doe nothing,</hi> wee haue not ſo much as the power ouer our naturall body, much leſſe ouer our ſpirituall.</p>
               <p>Then his <hi>Excell:</hi> ſaid, <hi>There bee ſome that would faine haue Repentance, but they cannot obtaine it;</hi> whereupon I anſwered, they that haue a true and hearty deſire vnto repentance, that is, the ſpirit of newneſſe of life, thoſe haue it already, and
<pb facs="tcp:191504:11"/> ſhall haue their deſire; ſuch hungry and thirſty ſoules the Lord will ſatisfie, ſaith Chriſt, partly here in this life, and perfectly in the life to come. And to this purpoſe tendeth that ſweet call of Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 11. <hi>Come all vnto mee, yee that are weary and heauy laden, and I will eaſe you.</hi> Hereby I tooke occaſion to relate vnto his <hi>Excell:</hi> the examples of two men, the one a Miniſter, who in his ſicknes, could not in his hart be perſwaded to relye vpon the mercy of God, which he would ſo faine haue done; the other, of a man who in his ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes complained of a hard &amp; ſtony heart, not being able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of his ſinnes which formerly hee had often done. His <hi>Excell:</hi> demanded how it went with them: the firſt (ſaid I) was of a Miniſter demanded, if he could not remember whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in former times hee had reioyced in the mercies of God, (he ſaid) yes, many times, then ſaid the Miniſter vnto him, Be of good comfort, when that darke cloud and houre of tryall ſhall bee paſt, it will come againe, and you ſhall haue your deſire, at which words the man ſo reioyced, and preſently prayſed the Lord, and thanked the Miniſter who ſpoke this comfort vnto him; ſaying, this comfort could not come into my minde. The other man had a Miniſter to come vnto him, and intreated him to pray vnto the Lord for him, and he himſelfe would pray alſo as much as he could, which he hauing diuers times done, found himſelfe to bee altered, wherefore he praiſed God, this ſaid his <hi>Excell:</hi> was well done. Then his <hi>Excell:</hi> demanded for ſome Chapters which trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of the Lords Prayer, and of the ioyes of heauen; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of hauing ſatisfied his <hi>Excell:</hi> I tooke my leaue of him, wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing him eaſe in this affliction, and a bleſſed ſucceſſe from the ſame: wherefore his <hi>Excell:</hi> did thanke me, ſaying, that hee could very well endure to haue mee come oftner vnto him.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:191504:11"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>This action laſted aboue an houre, hee being yet reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable ſtrong and able to ſpeake, and was very deſirous to heare the word of God.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>BEtweene the firſt and the ſecond viſitation on the faſting day, being the 6. of Aprill, I vnderſtood of Doctor <hi>Rumpf,</hi> Doctor vnto the King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> that his <hi>Excell:</hi> had his Bible lying open before him, of which I was very glad, and conſidering that when I was with his <hi>Excell:</hi> hee was twice deſirous to haue ſome places of Scripture read vnto him; not knowing if euer I ſhould ſee his <hi>Excell:</hi> any more, I thought good to ſend vnto him a note of certaine Chapters for him to reade, in regard he found himſelfe to bee reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble well, that ſo he might imploy his time in this exerciſe: and whereas the ſaid Doctor at that time was to goe vnto his <hi>Excell:</hi> I requeſted his worſhip to take this note along with him, and deliuer it vnto his <hi>Excell:</hi> intreating him to take notice of his <hi>Excell:</hi> diſpoſition, and accordingly, either to deliuer, or detaine it.</p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="letter">
                  <body>
                     <head>A note for his <hi>Excell:</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Examples of comfort for repentant ſinners, Luke chap.</hi> 15. <hi>and chap.</hi> 7. <hi>from the</hi> 36. <hi>verſe to the end, Pſal.</hi> 51. <hi>and</hi> 130.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>To comfort vs in the loue of Ieſus Chriſt, and to ſtirre vp our hearts vnto holy meditations, Iohn</hi> 17. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>To withdraw our hearts from earthly things, &amp; to moue vs to the deſire of the ioyes of heauen, the two laſt Chapters of the Reuelation.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <pb facs="tcp:191504:12"/>
               <p>The next day the ſaid Doctor told mee that hee had deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered it vnto his <hi>Excell:</hi> himſelfe, who preſently layd it in his Bible.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="visitation">
               <head>The ſecond Viſitation.</head>
               <p>ON the 12. of Aprill, being Tueſday, in the forenoone a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout tenne of the clocke, her <hi>Excell:</hi> the Princeſſe of <hi>Portugall,</hi> requeſted mee by a Meſſenger, to come vnto the Prince: In regard it was not likely that I ſhould ſtay there long, I went, and was preſently brought vnto his <hi>Excell:</hi> where I found not onely the ſaid Princeſſe of <hi>Portugall,</hi> but the Princeſſe of <hi>Orange</hi> that now is, with a great company of Lords, Nobles, Officers, the Lord <hi>Vosbergen,</hi> and others vnknowne vnto me, being come to his <hi>Excell:</hi> and being ſet downe at his beds ſide, I demanded of him how he felt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; whereupon he anſwered, I am well reſolued: thruſting vp his Cap from his eyes, he ſetled himſelfe to talke with me, and preſently ſpake theſe words. <hi>I haue read thoſe Chapters which you ſent vnto me, they were very excellent Chapters, I doe thanke you for them, but I cannot remember them all: I cannot repeate any particulars, but I haue remembred the ſubſtance, is not that well?</hi> Yes, gratious Lord (ſaid I) but your <hi>Excell:</hi> hath troubled your ſelfe too much, and that was not my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, for which I ſent them; for if your <hi>Excell:</hi> remember, I told you, you ſhould haue a verſe or two read vnto you, of that which ſhould come into your <hi>Excell:</hi> minde, that ſo you might imploy your minde in meditating on good thoughts, and not to reade whole Chapters, which were too tedious: But ſithence your <hi>Highneſſe</hi> hath pleaſed ſo to doe, the time is very well beſtowed, and I am ſure it will doe your <hi>Excell:</hi> good, for it is the holy word of God, written for our comfort. Your <hi>Excell:</hi> doth very well to keepe the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in your minde, <hi>which is the point of true Repentance, and the comfort thereof, and therein conſiſteth all?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Repentance hath theſe three branches,
<list>
                     <pb facs="tcp:191504:12"/>
                     <item>1 A true and vnfained ſorrow for ſinne.</item>
                     <item>2 Faith in Chriſt Ieſus.</item>
                     <item>3 A holy reſolution to amend our liues.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Whereupon his <hi>Excell:</hi> ſaid,<note place="margin">His <hi>Excell:</hi> doth confeſſe his ſinnes, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waileth that his repentance is not ſo well as it ought to be.</note> 
                  <hi>you doe very well ſometimes to come and viſite me:</hi> And then his <hi>Excell:</hi> ſpake with a ſpeciall earneſtneſſe: <hi>This is all that troubleth me, whether my repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance be ſufficient enough for my ſins, for I haue offended the Lord grieuouſly, and I conſtantly beleeue if I haue true repentance, that al my ſinnes are forgiuen; for Chriſt his ſake I will pray the Lord to giue me true repentance, more then I haue yet had:</hi> Hereupon I ſaid, your <hi>Excell:</hi> muſt not preſume vpon your Repentance, but with an humble and lowly heart, confeſſe and bewaile your ſinnes, as your <hi>Excell:</hi> alſo without doubt not fainedly, but from your heart, as it appeareth, and GOD knoweth it; and therefore your <hi>Excell:</hi> repentance is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to the repentance of al true repentant ſinners, which are ſet downe vnto vs in the word of God. Whereupon I did rehearſe vnto his <hi>Excell:</hi> the very words which the children of God had vſed at the time of their repentance, <hi>Eſay</hi> 6.4.6. <hi>Ierem.</hi> 14.20. of <hi>Dauid, Pſal</hi> 32.5.38.5.19.51. of the Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cane, <hi>Luke</hi> 18.13. of the Prodigall Sonne, <hi>Luke</hi> 15.18.19. &amp;c. And ſo I put his <hi>Excell:</hi> alſo in minde of that which hee had read in the aforeſaid Chapters. I ſaid further, it is a great matter to trouble ones ſelfe in the perfection of our repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: the man in the Goſpell ſaid, <hi>Lord, I beleeue,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Marke</hi> 9.24.</note> 
                  <hi>helpe thou mine vnbeliefe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Your <hi>Excell:</hi> knoweth, that here in this world wee can haue no perfection, neither of repentance, nor of faith: The godly lament their imperfections, and ſo doth your <hi>Excell:</hi> The moſt of our perfection in this life (ſaith an ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) conſiſteth in the acknowledgement and the bewayling of our imperfections. Therefore the more you are, (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the example of all the faithfull ſeruants of God) troubled with your ſinnes, (as appeareth by the trouble your <hi>Excell:</hi> hath of the ſufficiency of your Repentance) ſo much the more may you aſſure your ſelfe, that your repentance is
<pb facs="tcp:191504:13"/> vpright and acceptable vnto the Lord: <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith, <hi>I confeſſe my ſinnes;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal</hi> 38.</note> 
                  <hi>for there is no reſt in my bones, becauſe of my ſinnes: for mine iniquities are gone ouer my head, and as a waighty burthen they are too heauy for me.</hi> Your <hi>Excell:</hi> muſt alſo conſider the ſubtilty of the diuell, who as an enemie of our ſaluation, commonly towards our latter end doth moſt of al ſtriue with vs;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay</hi> 1 18. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.7.</note> but your <hi>Excell:</hi> muſt likewiſe know, that <hi>although our ſins were as Crimſon, they ſhall be made as white as Snow, euen through the precious bloud of Ieſus Chriſt, which clenſeth vs from all our ſinnes:</hi> and therefore conſequently that our Faith and Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance is vnperfect. Vpon ſuch repentance as this your <hi>Excell:</hi> repentance is, the Lord will without doubt worke in your heart a ſpeciall ioy and comfort, and ſo I ſhewed vnto his <hi>Excell:</hi> from the Pſalms of <hi>Dauid,</hi> that his repentance was true repentance: &amp; when I had rehearſed ſome places of Scripture to confirme it, &amp; to comfort his <hi>Excell:</hi> he anſwered, <hi>I will pray the Lord to ſtrengthen mee:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">His <hi>Ex:</hi> is well contented, and is reſolued.</note> 
                  <hi>I am now at reſt, and am reſolued.</hi> Whereupon I committed him to the Lord and tooke my leaue of him, and before I went away, her <hi>Excell:</hi> the Princeſſe of <hi>Portugal</hi> requeſted me to come in the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone againe. I ſaid, I was loath to bee ouer trouble-ſome vnto his <hi>Excell:</hi> but I was the more emboldned, becauſe doctor <hi>Roſeus,</hi> Miniſter of the word of God at the <hi>Hage,</hi> told me that he had beene with his <hi>Excell:</hi> and found him very well at reſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="visitation">
               <head>The third viſitation.</head>
               <p>THe ſame day about three of the clocke in the afternoone their <hi>Excellencies</hi> the Princeſſe of <hi>Portugal</hi> and <hi>Orange</hi> did let mee vnderſtand that they were with the <hi>Prince,</hi> and that they did expect me there, Whereupon I went, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming thither, I found the <hi>Prince</hi> very weake of body but of good comfort;<note place="margin">His <hi>Ex:</hi> is of good comfort.</note> for when I aſked his <hi>Excell:</hi> whether hee was well at reſt, He anſwered, <hi>yes as well as euer hee was.</hi> Then I ſaid, the Lord bee praiſed for it; vpon ſuch repentance and faith as I haue found in your <hi>Excell:</hi> I did expect this mercy
<pb facs="tcp:191504:13"/> from the Lord, &amp; that according to the promiſe of Chriſt, to <hi>eaſe them that are weary and heauy laden that come vnto him; and to giue the victory to them that doe fight ſo well:</hi> Such a quiet peace and reſt is the life of our ſoules, yea, it is the Kingdome of God within vs. And here I exhorted his <hi>Excell:</hi> to continue ſo vnto the end, rehearſing certaine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, wherein the Lord doth promiſe the helpe and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuation of his mercy vntill the end. Wee poore ſinners are bound to vſe the meanes which the Lord hath ordained, but without the holy Ghoſt this worke cannot be vndertaken nor continued. His <hi>Excell:</hi> ſaid, <hi>So doe I hold it to bee alſo; It muſt all come from God, and I will pray him to ſtrengthen mee.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">His <hi>Ex:</hi> chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an declaration of Gods mercy.</note> Hereby I tooke courrage to ſpeake thus vnto his <hi>Excell:</hi> Gratious Lord, your <hi>Excell:</hi> hath ſpoken very religiouſly, ſaying, <hi>that it must all come from the Lord,</hi> and that <hi>you will pray vnto the Lord to ſtrengthen you;</hi> The Lord will bee prayed or his mercies, and that honour doth onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long vnto him, and wee ought to doe it with a willing mind, and with all chearfulneſſe, and that in regard hee doth ſo gratiouſly promiſe to heare vs. The Apoſtle <hi>Iames</hi> doth alſo exhort vs to this duty, <hi>If any bee ſicke among you</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>let him call for thee elders of the church,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iames</hi> 5.14.</note> 
                  <hi>and let them pray for him.</hi> May it therefore pleaſe your <hi>Excell:</hi> that we doe al loyntly call vpon the name of the Lord, and you to pray with vs, as much as is in your power. His <hi>Excell:</hi> anſwered, <hi>when you pleaſe.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">His <hi>Ex:</hi> is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to haue payers ſaid at his beds ſide.</note> Whereupon we all fell vpon our knees before the Lord, and prayed with teares. Prayer being ended, I ſet my ſelfe downe againe to comfort his <hi>Excell:</hi> as the Lord ſhould put it into my minde, amongſt other things ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the pleaſant fruits of affliction, and of the difference betweene the death of the Saints and the wicked, and of the profitable change which they doe make, who in true faith end their pilgrimage, out of this vale of miſery, leauing theſe earthly tabernacles, and goe to dwell with the Lord, and how happy and how precious death is vnto them, becauſe it end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth their miſery, and doth tranſport them vnto the deſired hauen of reſt, euen the Kingdome of glory. At theſe ſpeeches
<pb facs="tcp:191504:14"/> his <hi>Excellencie</hi> harkened with an extraordinary attention, turning himſelfe vnto mee, and looking very ſtedfaſtly vpon mee, which made me to admire it; at length with great reioycing, hee approued my words, ſaying, <hi>So doe I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue alſo, I am reſolued;</hi> then I ſaid vnto his <hi>Excell:</hi> It plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed GOD to let mee adminiſter his holy word vnto his <hi>Excell:</hi> of happy memory, <hi>Count William</hi> of <hi>Naſſau,</hi> in the time of his ſickeneſſe, and ſo God hath ordained, that I ſhould doe vnto your Highneſſe, although in great weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, I doe therefore in all humility beſeech your Highneſſe, graciouſly to ponder this my meane ſeruice vnto you, tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting that it will not goe without a bleſſing from the LORD, for I know with what heart I haue done it; whereupon his <hi>Excell:</hi> ſaid, <hi>I thanke you for troubling your ſelfe ſo much with my perſon;</hi> and preſently after, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I did not well vnderſtand his <hi>Excell:</hi> hee ſaid, <hi>You haue done me very good ſeruice.</hi> And when I thought herewith to haue taken my leaue of his <hi>Excell:</hi> his <hi>Excell:</hi> kiſſed his hand and reached it forth vnto mee, ſo that it made the teares to runne downe my eyes, ſaying; your <hi>Excell:</hi> may pleaſe to bee of good comfort, and and without doubt the LORD will giue you a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py iſſue from this affliction. And ſo I withdrew my ſelfe, hauing taken my leaue of the ſaid Princeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</p>
               <p>In this action, although I was very weary of body, yet I reioyced in GOD, and ſo did both the ſaid Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes, Prayſing the Lord, in the midſt of their ſorrow, for the Religious and Chriſtian behauiour of his <hi>Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="visitation">
               <pb facs="tcp:191504:14"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The fourth Viſitation.</hi> Being on Wedneſday the 13. of Aprill in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone, about 10. of the clocke, which was his <hi>Excell:</hi> dying-day.</head>
               <p>AT this time was I fetched againe to come vnto his <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell:</hi> whom I found to be much altered, and be was not likely to liue long; although, when I asked his <hi>Excell:</hi> how he felt himſelfe, he ſaid, <hi>It is much alike as it was yeſterday.</hi> And whereas I perceiued his <hi>Excell:</hi> to be very weake, I comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him with theſe places of Scripture, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.13. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.15.16. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28.38.39. Whereupon his <hi>Excell:</hi> anſwered, <hi>I am reſolued, and there is nothing in the world that troubleth me,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Very religious words of his <hi>Excell:</hi> before his death.</note> 
                  <hi>onely this; whether my Repentance be as ſufficient for my ſinnes, as it ought to be; I am ſorry that I cannot ſerue the Lord as I would doe; The Lord ſtrengthen me; I am at reſt.</hi> With theſe words his <hi>Excell:</hi> gaue ſufficiently to vnderſtand, that he was at reſt in his minde. Wherefore with all my power and ability, I ſought more and more to ſtrengthen his <hi>Excell:</hi> in this particular, whereunto I found my ſelfe much addicted: and to this end I put his <hi>Excell:</hi> in minde of all the ſpeeches which hee had ſpoken; and firſt, I put him in minde of his repentance for his ſinnes; ſecondly, of his faith in <hi>Ieſus Chriſt;</hi> and thirdly, of his religious purpoſe to amend his life: all which ſpeeches I approued with the word of God, and thereupon I told his <hi>Excell:</hi> that we were commanded, to them that were thus prepared, to lay open vnto them the whole treaſure of Gods mercy, and his faithfull promiſes in <hi>Chriſt Ieſus:</hi> Wherefore your <hi>Excell:</hi> muſt make a good vſe of this affliction, and by the fruits thereof, ſhew and acknowledge the loue of God, according to his word, <hi>for he correcteth him whom he loueth:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 3.12.</note> And your <hi>Excell:</hi> ſhall finde that death is life, according to Gods promiſe, <hi>He that beleeueth in me,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.6.</note> 
                  <hi>it paſſed from death vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to life. I deſire,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul, to be looſed, and to be with Chriſt;
<pb facs="tcp:191504:15"/> for death vnto me is aduantage;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.23.21. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1.</note> 
                  <hi>If our earthly tabernacles be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed we haue a building giuen vs of God in the heauens.</hi> And thus I exhorted his <hi>Excell:</hi> to ſet himſelfe at peace, reioycing in his Sauiour <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> in whoſe name, I (as a ſeruant of Chriſt) did pronounce vnto his <hi>Excell:</hi> forgiueneſſe of all his ſinnes, which he did from his heart repent of; which the Lord himſelfe doth promiſe to ratifie and approue: Your <hi>Excell:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 18 18.</note> ſaid I, hath euer beene a ſincere Prince, hating all falſhood and lyes, and your <hi>Excell:</hi> hath alſo meant it with your heart, whatſoeuer you haue ſaid in the premiſſes; for your <hi>Excell:</hi> knoweth, that this is not a time to flatter any body in ſo weighty a matter as this is, whereon your <hi>Excell:</hi> ſaluation dependeth: Therefore your <hi>Excell:</hi> may pleaſe to bee ſtedfaſt in the onely comfort wee haue both in life and death; and wherein your <hi>Excell:</hi> hath beene ſo long reſolued to liue and dye in, with the children of God, without whom I doe here proteſt before the Lord, to know no other ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for my ſelfe,<note place="margin">His <hi>Excell:</hi> laſt words. Of his conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedneſſe in the true comfort of the children of God.</note> nor for any other Chriſtian: whereupon I demanded his <hi>Excell,</hi> of this comfort, out of the firſt queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>high-dutch Catechiſme;</hi> His <hi>Excell:</hi> anſwered, <hi>This is my onely comfort: I know none other, and this is my onely refuge, whereby I purpoſe to remaine:</hi> which ſweet words of his <hi>Excell:</hi> were as a Crowne to this holy worke, and a certaine ſigne that the ſpirit of God had throughly wrought in his heart. Then I ſaid vnto his <hi>Excell:</hi> your <hi>Excell:</hi> may now expect (ouer and aboue the Lawrell wreath wherewith the Lord hath crowned you here in this life) to be crowned (with all thoſe Kings and Princes, that with true faith haue kiſſed the Sonne of God) (as your <hi>Excell:</hi> hath done) with an immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall and euerlaſting Crowne of glory in the world to come. After theſe words were ended, his <hi>Excell:</hi> ſaid, (though with great trouble) <hi>I cannot well ſpeake any more:</hi> whereupon I left his <hi>Excell:</hi> wiſhing him a happy end, which I ſaw to draw neare. At this Viſitation were preſent the chiefeſt Officers of his <hi>Excellencie.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="last" type="visitation">
               <pb facs="tcp:191504:15"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The laſt Viſitation.</hi> When his <hi>Excellencie</hi> lay a dying, and departed this world.</head>
               <p>IN the afternoone about foure of the clocke, I was by two Sergeants requeſted to come vp vnto his <hi>Excell:</hi> Being come into the Chamber, I found his <hi>Excell:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">His <hi>Excell:</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſpeake any more, but hath his perfect vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding.</note> to be toward his laſt end, his ſpeech hauing left him, and was not able once to caſt vp his eyes. I ſpake at his <hi>Excell:</hi> eare, Being your <hi>Excell:</hi> ſpeech doth now faile you, thinke now in your heart (which the Lord doth behold and ſearch thorow) vpon your Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> who is now the onely life and comfort of your <hi>Excell:</hi> And when I did perceiue his <hi>Excell:</hi> gaue ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient ſignes that he vnderſtood me, I did, at the requeſt of the Princeſſe of <hi>Portugall</hi> (who ſtood by mee, and with wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping eyes beheld his <hi>Excell:</hi>) ſay prayers,<note place="margin">Prayers is ſaid.</note> there being like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe preſent, the Comitties of the High and Mighty, the Lords Eſtates generall, the Lord <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>osbergen,</hi> and other Lords to me vnknowne, alſo the chiefeſt ſeruants of his Highneſſe, with two Doctors, Doctor <hi>Rumpf,</hi> and Doctor <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alentius,</hi> who did all fall vpon their knees before the Lord, and prayed with bitter teares for his <hi>Excell.</hi> After prayer was ended, I ſpake againe at his <hi>Excell:</hi> eare; ſaying, If your <hi>Excell:</hi> hath vnderſtood me, and that you are yet comforted in the Lord,<note place="margin">His <hi>Excell.</hi> gaue a ſign to ſhew that hee did vnderſtand it, and that he was well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented.</note> I pray let me know by touching my hand; whereupon his <hi>Ex:</hi> preſently hold me ſo faſt by my hand, that I could ſcarce get it out, vntill ſuch time as the ſtrength of his life went from him; and then I ſpake once more theſe words vnto him, <hi>Lord Ieſu receiue my ſpirit, Lord Ieſu haue mercy vpon me.</hi> His <hi>Excell:</hi> did yet ſufficiently ſhew that hee vnderſtood it; whereupon we once againe went vnto prayers, and prayed with ſuch fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uency, as any Chriſtian might imagine.<note place="margin">Prayer is ſaid once more.</note> And afterwards be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene 5. and 6. of the clocke, this noble Prince reſted in the Lord, in the prayers of the beholders, ſo ſweetly, as euer I
<pb facs="tcp:191504:16"/> ſaw man dye, without the leaſt motion of his body, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any interruption of his breath.<note place="margin">His <hi>Excell:</hi> pleaſant death.</note> And thus dyed this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Champion, <hi>Prince Maurice, &amp;c.</hi> in the 58. yeare of his age, hauing Gouerned little leſſe then 40. yeares. Hee was held of all true-hearted Patriots, a precious and choſen Inſtrument of Gods glory, ſpecially for Gods Church, and theſe Countries. He will be by ſome more lamented after his death,<note place="margin">An Exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vnto all the Inhabitants of this Land.</note> then he was beloued of them in his life. But I pray and exhort all faithfull Inhabitants of this Land, to take to heart theſe few enſuing admonitions wherewith I will conclude this my Narration.</p>
               <p>The Lord hath within theſe few yeares taken from vs that faithfull Prince <hi>Count William Lodowicke</hi> of <hi>Naſſau,</hi> &amp;c. and hath ſithence viſited this Land with heauy plagues, famine, high-waters, ſtrong-warres, as is yet at this time, beſides the extraordinary beſieging of the City of <hi>Breda,</hi> and now moreouer ſmites vs for our ſinnes with this deepe wound; and that in ſuch a time, when all the world would iudge we ſtood in moſt neede of this great Prince. <hi>Will the Lord then vtterly forſake vs and goe from vs?</hi> It ſeemeth ſo: and certainely this is no vaine imagination, but the King of all Kings, and the Lord of all Lords, whoſe iudgements are iuſt, and whoſe wayes are vnſearchable, can and will (according to his infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite mercy who hath ſo many times miraculouſly ſaued theſe Countries, for his holy name, and welbeloued Sonnes ſake) keepe vs, if wee, (as well Rulers as Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects) doe hate our ſinnes, betimes turne vnto him, and doe vprightly walke before him, in his holy lawes which are not vnknowne vnto vs.</p>
               <p>And this is that which wee muſt doe, if wee will make a good vſe of Gods iudgements, that he may turne them from vs, and if wee deſire to haue the Lord to bleſſe this Countrey and State; otherwiſe wee all ſee, if wee are not blinde in heart, how the LORD doth threaten vs, and which certainely once will come vpon vs, if wee remaine ſnorting in our carnall ſecurity, and
<pb facs="tcp:191504:16"/> then wee ſhall not finde any mercy with the LORD. It is not any inward nor outward meanes will bee able to ſaue vs, if the LORD turne from vs: And therefore thoſe are the beſt people, who aboue all things ſeeke to appeaſe the wrath of the moſt Higheſt, who ruleth the hearts of all Kings, and ſo labour to obtaine his fauour, that with a good conſcience they may both liue and dye in his feare, and thereunto they vſe all poſſible meanes, according to their vocation, to employ it for the ſeruice of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good; and this confirmeth a State, and bringeth the bleſſing of God ouer the whole Countrey; but here I take leaue with the Prophet <hi>Ieremie,</hi> to ſay; <hi>O earth, earth, earth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ier.</hi> 22.29.</note> 
                  <hi>heare the word of the LORD:</hi> What word? the word of the Sonne of GOD: <hi>Remember from whence thou art fallen, and repent, and doe thy firſt workes, or elſe I will come againſt thee ſhortly, and will remoue your Candleſticke out of his place, except thou amend.</hi> I pray the Lord this may bee well practiſed. That all higher powers, and thoſe of meaner ſort would take example of the Religious and godly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe of this Noble Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> whoſe ſoule vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly is now in glory with the Lord <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> waiting for the bleſſed reſurrection of the dead, which the Lord of his mercy grant vnto vs. Vnto whom, as moſt due is, bee all honour, prayſe, and glory, for euermore, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For as much as concernes thoſe that harden themſelues in their ſinnes, by the abuſing of Gods mercy, and by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of thoſe Saints that haue fallen, and are riſen vp againe, (for ſuch there euer hath beene, and yet are) muſt know if they haue not a deſire of their condemnation, <hi>Quod non ſint exempla cadendi, nec in peccatis iacendi, ſed cauendi &amp; ſi cecideris, reſurgendi;</hi> that is to ſay, that thoſe be no examples to fall, nor yet to lye ſtill, but take heed wee doe not fall or if wee bee fallen, that wee riſe vp againe. Who is ſo fooliſh that will goe breake his owne ſhinnes, becauſe hee ſeeth his fellow by a fall hath broken his, and is whole
<pb facs="tcp:191504:17"/> againe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.12.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhall wee continue ſtill in ſinne, that grace may abound? God forbid;</hi> they that are led by the ſpirit of GOD, are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraide of ſuch thoughts, for ſo much as concerneth the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, with all his wicked complices, and vncleane ſpirits, who cannot endure, and doe nothing but ſcorne and deride the children of God, in whom the Angels doe reioyce. Wee muſt not ſtumble at theſe, for Chriſt himſelfe ſaith in the Goſpell, that their iudgement will bee hard enough for them to beare; and therfore it is needleſſe here to ſpeake any more of them, and therefore I end: Beſeeching the Lord to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine the diuell, and mercifully to ſaue his people in this great tempeſt, wherein the whole Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian world doe ſo fearefully ſtriue with one another.</p>
               <closer>So be it.</closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
